2025.)
>> good afternoon and welcome
to the san francisco board of
supervisors regular meeting this
afternoon at 2:00 pm., tuesday,
JANUARY 14, 2025. Um, MADAM
Clerk, call the roll.
>> >> thank you, MR.
PRESIDENT.
>> supervisor chan, present.
>> confirmed, present.
>> supervisor dorsey, present.
>> supervisor engardio,
present.
>> supervisor fielder,
>> supervisor mahmood not
present supervisor melgar,
present.
>> supervisor melgar, present.
>> supervisor sauter, present.
>> supervisor sherrill,
present.
>> supervisor walton and
supervisor mahmood, present.
>> MR. PRESIDENT all members
are present.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk >>
unceded ancestral homeland of
the ramaytush (Rah-my-toosh)
Ohlone (O-lon-ee) Who are the
original inhabitants of the san
francisco peninsula.
Responsibilities as the
caretakers of this place, as
well as for all peoples who
reside in their traditional
territory.
Elders, and relatives of the
ramaytush ohlone community and
by affirming their sovereign
rights as first peoples.
>> colleagues will you join me
in reciting the pledge of
allegiance.
Of the united states of
and to the republic for which it
stands, one nation under GOD,
indivisible, with liberty and
justice for all.
>> on behalf of the board I'd
like to acknowledge the staff
that sfgovtv who record each of
the meetings and make the
transcripts to the public you
believe that is-thank you,
james. I also ask that everyone
bear with me susceptible through
the errors of the first meeting
MADAM Clerk, any accomodation.
>> yes. Thank you, MR.
PRESIDENT.
Prior to the hearing MAY be
delivered to the clerk of the
board or the clerk of the
committee and will be shared
with the members.
>> meetings are cablecast on
sfgovtv, atwww.Sfgovtv.Org or
cable channels 26, 28, 78 or 99
(Depending on your provider).
For petroleum send an e-mail to
sfgov or post service to the
board of supervisors the city
hall, 1 DR. Carlton b. Goodlett
place, san francisco, ca 94102
room 244 san francisco,
california. To make a reasonable
accommodation americans with
disabilities act or to request
language assistance
to raise your hand for public
comment on a specific agenda
item press-
3 when prompted by
the meeting moderator. Thank
you, MR. PRESIDENT. And members.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk >>
um, we have our minutes.
>> approval of the NOVEMBER 19,
2024, DECEMBER 3, 2024, and
december 10, 2024,
regular board meeting minutes.
>> any changes to those
meeting minutes I don't think so
seeing none, can I have motion
to approve the minutes as
presented moved by supervisor
melgar and seconded by
supervisor walton MADAM Clerk,
call the roll.
>> >> supervisor chen, aye.
>> supervisor dorsey, aye.
>> supervisor engardio, aye.
>> supervisor fielder, aye.
>> supervisor mahmood, aye.
>> PRESIDENT Mandelman, aye.
>> supervisor melgar, aye.
>> supervisor sauter, aye.
>> supervisor sherrill, aye.
>> supervisor walton, aye.
>> and xhavrnd, aye.
>> 11 ayes how without
objection minutes will be
approved after public comment as
presented and MADAM Clerk could
you call
you call our.
>> unfinished business:
ordinance amending the planning
code and zoning map to create
the 30 van ness avenue
quality act; making findings of
consistency with the general
plan, and the eight priority
policies of planning code,
section 101.1; and findings.
Supervisor dorsey thank you,
supervisor mandelman I've been
working closely with room 200
and others to make sure district
6 can moved and 30 van ness is
an stance the developer started
the project in AUGUST of 2022
and affordable housing fee
indexes to the city up front on
site permits that is at a
critical intersection at van
ness and multi-family has
visually stalled. For some time
my office has been working
closely with the oewd to jump in
start the project but paused the
legislation before seeks to
improve the projects feasibility
and main the benefits proposed
on the public arraign my office
makes sure the fees are with the
both sides instructions citywide
in the current market at at cap
and guidelines today 345e789sz
will build on the land use
committee put forward make the
changes to the certain numbers
and provide credit for the
fooeshgz this colleagues will
fully lion van ness with the
objections other projects are
subject to and get closures
closer to the construction
underway and summarize the
minutes first deletion on page 8
line 21 adding language to
provide impact fees and third
and finally on page 9 line 6
regarding the section 415 I'd
like to express my thanks to
supervisor melgar for helping
and my colleagues hope to have
this motion and underlying
motion I'd like to have a motion
for the circulated amendments
and vote as amended with the
first reading.
>> thank you, supervisor dorsey
>> supervisor melgar thank
you, supervisor mandelman first,
I'd like to second the motion
supervisor dorsey. I wanted to
tell you colleagues, we heard
this in committee. There was
disagreements at the last
committee meeting I voted
against the amendment because
they-the whole point to move
this project forward. Many of us
come to work in this building
every single day see that
project a hole in the ground. At
the corner of market street and
there were during the pandemic
wood structures built around
this we say a lot of hurt at
that um, intersection a lot of
our neighbors suffering from
addiction and homelessness. And
it was definitely, you know, one
of the soar points in the
corridor I'm eager to make sure
we um, keep our promises to the
community and serve the
community benefits and allow the
project to forward I want to say
during the land use committee
didn't get a huge outpouring of
the community support for the
amendment nor opposition to the
project. It wasn't for the what
happened here. And, you know, I
will be supporting supervisor
dorsey in the work he's doing in
his district and hope to move
forward.
>> thank you supervisor melgar.
>> again supervisor dorsey
your staff supported the
amendments seeing today city
attorneys are not here so no
vote.
>> good afternoon. Deputy
city attorney the amendments by
supervisor dorsey are not
substantive and no go back to
the committee.
>> all right. So no questions
or comments there has been a
motion on the amendments second
MADAM Clerk, call the roll.
>> other than the amendments.
>> on the amendments.
>> xhvrn, aye.
>> as supervisor dorsey, aye.
>> supervisor engardio, aye.
>> supervisor fielder, aye.
>> supervisor mahmood, aye.
>> PRESIDENT Mandelman, aye.
>> supervisor melgar, aye.
>> supervisor sauter, aye.
>> supervisor sherrill, aye.
>> supervisor walton, aye.
>> supervisor chan, aye.
>> there are 11 ayes.
>> all right. And then I
think I need a motion on the
amended on the amended items so
that moved by supervisor dorsey
and seconded by supervisor
melgar.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection the motion
passed on this firefighters.
>> as amended.
>> thank you.
>> let's go to roll call for
introductions.
>> first today is supervisor
chen.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk and
thank you, supervisor mandelman.
>> and colleagues today, I'm
very honored and excited in my
first official meeting as to
introduce a resolution
celebrating 2020 as is most of
the snake and celebration of the
new year in to has become a
culturally significant event
that became with the one the
first day of new year and evens
on the full moon the increasing
is a significant holiday for
asian families to get together
and honor the ancestors with
hopes of prosperity and good
health and celebration and
traditional food this is the
2020 year the snake promises to
bring a transformation and I'd
like to thank all my colleagues
for their unanimous
co-sponsoring and supervisor
chan for her sponsorship.
>> thank you supervisor chen.
>> supervisor dorsey.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk I'll
stand because I understand a
photo op.
>> colleagues, I'm not
introducing legislation myself I
would like to offer support for
mayor-elect daniel lurie be able
legislation was introduced and
after it briefly on they
proposal I asked the boards to
be a sponsor this challenge is
personal as many of you know. I
don't think there is a single
problem facing san francisco
today not wholly drink or made
worse by addictions and the
worst culprit this one drug is
driving health
more and mayor-elect
daniel lurie to put the
resources where they're needed
in the approach to contract
processes and we hope to start
the solutions as the problems we
face my strong support and hope
I'm a enjoy strong support from
the
matters that are within the
commission's jurisdiction.
Thank you.
>> thank you very much.
Colleagues today, I'm the first
introduction of legislation,
aye.
>> a supervisor 3 reaffirm our
commitment to the sanctuary
ordinance in effect for 35 years
jp morgan chase passed the first
ordinance in the country in
response to a tax on
get-togethers on the regular
administration hearsay of cities
have adopt their own sanctuary
ordinances modeled after ours
the MISS Conception just to be
clear, sanctuary ordinances
prohibits the city resources and
personnel from evaluating the
federal government with
targeting arrest and detaining
immigrants unless required by
the state law it is public
right-of-way for all san
franciscans by insuring all
residents regardless of the
immigration status to call fire
department agencies and police
department in public
right-of-ways situations and
promotes public health and
education all families
regardless of immigration status
feel safe. Sorry all the
sanctuary all families in the
immigration status feel safe at
the public health services and
sending the kid to the public
schools and last night I
attended an immigration
commission on this topic of prep
the community for the upcoming
federal administration including
the projects promises to create
the largest deportation program
in history and last night's
hearing was well attended the
overflow room was at capacity
and registrar-recorder/county
clerk interpretation in four
languages I want to thank the
office of immigration affairs
for their language
interpretation. To the
immigration rights commission
and a hearing and to the
community partners with the
presentations I heard loud and
clear gkts are looking for us
for shawnee to stand by this I
heard many people in my district
and across the cities are waking
up in a state of anxiety what it
or is to come and some parents
stopped sending their kids to
school afraid to report
emergencies and some don't know
how to look their children in
the face and tell them it is
going to be okay and finally
from elected officers that
anxiety not what san francisco
is about. This town was built
by people who are immigrant and
wouldn't function without people
who migrate and because we get a
new PRESIDENT We'll not
abandoned our community but our
sanctuary city ordinance is here
to stay.
>> thank you every single one
of the board supervisor melgar
and supervisor chan and all.
Thank you very much. Thank you,
thank you supervisor fielder.
>> supervisor mahmood.
>> yes. I'd like to make two
condominiums and introduce one
motion as well. I want to second
supervisor dorseys co-sponsoring
for the mayors statement of
emergency I'm proud to be a
co-children and the reason is
because this type of focus and
decisive action to address the
concerns about fentanyl and it's
devastating impacts and critical
step in treating the demand a
bold measure to make sure that
the process is not mired in
bureaucracy and want to commend
those-I'm supporting to
quickly address mental health
and public safety by reducing
the administrative delays the
city can move quickly to expand
the services and provided
critical resources. We did this
during covid and replicating the
powers to the mayor's office to
shut this down pandemic as a
epidemic and and accountability
framework robust controls for
audits for responsible
implementation will add to the
safeguards to tackle this I
believe with the tools we can
restore hope and improve public
safety to our community and I'm
happy to sponsor with supervisor
dorsey in the capacity. The
second thing I want to comment
on is another critical issue
having in district 5 the pending
closure of giveaway in the I
want to call I'll be filing
paperwork to have a hearing on
behalf of the community and the
community asked for it for
several reasons one our office
has received calls and met with
the members of the public who
shared their concerns about loas
the service and pharmaceutical
and banking services provide
necessary sisters enacting the
refugees in the western addition
and journey
apantown and yesterday, I
personally went to the community
and clerks and store managers no
more produce and likely not
reoriented. There is
pharmaceutical services until he
FEBRUARY 7th you but make sure
you're finding ways to transfer
those going forward and this
impeding closing date long term
to make sure there is minimal
services in the neighborhood we
know the community has been told
this for a while and the loss
that is of the by the residents
and deserve to be heard I'll be
introducing in the land use
committee this measure
supervisor melgar in the hearing
so the community can be heard
and have transparent about the
project and what we'll do now
and next and to give them the
answers they're looking for and
again, want to acknowledge the
commitment and the advocacy for
the community and by day and
working with the partnering over
the coming years. Thank you.
(Clapping.)
Thank you, supervisor mahmood.
>> PRESIDENT Mandelman and I
have nothing to submit.
>> thank you, MR. PRESIDENT,
and supervisor melgar. Thank
you. MADAM Clerk.
>> I will also start by
welcoming all the our newly
elected colleagues and reelected
colleagues so I'm hopeful we
will work together to workout
things together and with that,
I'll take the opportunity to
tell you what I will be prior
pifrgz if it sounds too good to
be true, it probably is.
This coming year and we have
different, you know, interest
rates
(Laughter)
And, you know, so no surprise my
are on the land use and
transportation so I want to make
sure we um, fulfill our
commitment to the state on our
housing element with our
affordable housing commitment.
And all of the legislation that
we didn't get to. We have a
deadline by the independence of
this year and I'll be doing
doing everything we can to make
sure we negotiate with each
other and with the state and the
mayor's office to get to the
finish line. I'll be
concentrating on the legislation
to finalize the co-op housing
legislation I've been working on
to quite a while and required
the focus on the state
delegation and financing of the
co-op housing has to do with
with the state law needs to be
changed to help us to get to the
finish line and I'm committed to
that and really committed to
making sure that we at state
community service nothing more
regressive than to cut back on
public and assessable
transportation. Um, but
PRESIDENT Mandelman and I have
been part of muni giving up to
get our heads with regard around
what all the stakeholders have
been thinking about in terms of
balancing the muni budget and
putting forth a plan that was
submitted and um, last but not
least I'll make sure that
children in our cities are
supported in their success on
the childcare it takes time and
have not gotten to and the
services that provide children
in the public schools and the
way to economic recovery through
all of the housing through
transportation and to taking
care of our future residents. So
residents for the future
taxpayers I'm committed to that
and with that, I have address a
request that is the closure of
wall green on the border of
district 7 have lost 4 stores in
the past 5 years and last to
death and two walgreens and
they're large, you know,
storefronts so I'm making a
request for the city attorney
for some planning code changes
to make this easier to fulfill
the large storefronts and this
serve as neighbors to the
neighborhood commercial kroerd
/-
corridor and on the things in
san francisco besides the 1 on
ocean avenue we have spent time
and emergency I want to make
sure we have an easier minded
with that and restore public
transparent and last a in
memoriam close the meeting in
honor of colonel peter who was a
dear friend gentle kind friend.
He was born on JANUARY 29, 1939,
in new york's and passed away
think DECEMBER 5th. He grew up
in the bronx and went around the
world with service in
distinction in korea and was a
resident of west portal for
decades. And married to barbara
raised three children attended
the schools in san francisco.
And just wendy and survived by
four grandchildren and survived
by several siblings gene and
charles and colonel was a
graduate of west point and
served in the U.S. Army and it's
final assignment was detective
commander at the presidio san
francisco in the army after a
very successful military career
consider necessarily and I
served together on the board of
directors at the jewish council
and voted a big part of his life
supporting veterans on you've
duty especially the veterans
that suffer from std and
homelessness and needed on enter
-he spent allotment in care
with everyone he met with the
developers who needed the extra
help and transferred in the
military to work force and was a
generous compassionate leader
husband and father and coach and
friend so jcrc gave him an award
in 2018 and many more deserving
and I'll MISS Him dealer and
send his love to barbara and his
children we'll MISS You pete.
The rest I submit.
>> >> thank you supervisor
melgar.
>> supervisor sauter thank
you, MADAM Clerk.
>> colleagues, I come to the
office running a campaign and
over those thousands of
incredible conversations heard
dreams of lower cost of living
by building more housing for
homelessness and for better
neighborhood schools but heard a
constant desire to do maul
things we're to earn the trust
of our residents back it is
important we do the maul things
well and nothing is more
important that's why I'm asking
for a hearing calling on the
city's policy and progress that
relates to this we have
questions and looking for
answers resident want to know
how to address the track cans
and businesses why the trash
cans on the corner is over
flowing and tourist wonder why
they have to wake 6 to 8 blocks
we know that happens to the
fancy trash cans but by some
accounts our city has 15 hundred
trash cans from years ago and
our budget is larger I look
forward to the working with the
department of public works and
to have more trash cans and
cleaner streets. The rest I
submit.
>> thank you, supervisor
sauter.
>> supervisor sherrill.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk >>
MR. PRESIDENT and colleagues
thank you to supervisor engardio
and echo the comments by
supervisor dorsey and supervisor
melgar proud to will be a
co-sponsor san franciscans
demand action. Do I want to
introduce and request for the
study for the impacts explore
how to extend those key waivers
for the future and san francisco
commercial corridors with the
backbone of the city and with
the accessibility and
walkability our city small
businesses have a profound
impact on the neighborhoods with
the success of each commercial
corridor where on lombard those
stops and gathering places are
the life blood of our community
and consistency but we have
struggled with the barriers like
startup costs and rising
expenses continue to make is
challenging for small businesses
to open and thrive in the city
we must continue to make 3
easier for small business owners
to succeed. First to achieve
this hearing will analyze this
program with the exception and
examine remaining barriers for
the implementations and identify
the steps to make small
businesses scheme permanent with
those fee waivers to expire on
the first starting discussions
how to extend the programs I
look forward to working with
each of you and with the small
businesses to make sure that san
francisco remains a city where
small businesses grow and thrive
and enrich the city for years to
come. The rest I submit.
>> thank you, supervisor
sherrill.
>> supervisor walton.
>> we're doing something new
for initiatives or in any case
lack of support but I do want to
say in response to the mayors
fentanyl proposal and action
that one thing we should
understand is during covid we
gave emergency powers to the
mayor with the presence of a
sporadic plan. Right now we have
legislation that requests
waiving process to allow for the
swift sdibts and supporting this
legislation is premature without
the presence of a plan that
demonstrates exactly what the
mayor and the city plans to do.
I look forward to learning more
about this specific of a plan.
Um, I am not sure how to
understand that by. The rest I
submit.
>> at the supervisor walton.
>> supervisor chan submit
thank you.
Seeing no other names on the
roster, includes the
introduction of the new comment.
>> public comment and please
line up on our right-hand side
the chamber and speak to the
approval of the minutes or
general matters that are not on
today's matter but on is board
jurisdictions all others will be
-we are setting the timer for
two minutes.
>> yes. We'll collect them.
Thank you.
>> we're setting the timer
for two minutes and great this
is very truth without setting
I'm not the trust. That was you
don't use trust so. You can't
stop I can't stop with
everything with the-la which
thanks to whatever said
(Unintelligible) Fine.
>> now because you have to
open your eyes this is not the
first time this happened this
trying everything today will-
there is something to remember
understand I creation is-
(Unintelligible) For the better
so if you destroy your means of
creation you don't create
anything therefore you set
limitation we took the future to
reconnect human beings. With
(Unintelligible).
>> animals.
>> make sure that every single
human being would be better
serviced with the species to
take care of for 5 years.
Everyone. The criminals wouldn't
be part of
(Bell ringing)
If given a specific oh,
recognized sort of animals now,
if you keep doing what you're
doing fine I hope you are sure
you'll never be (Unintelligible)
In in any way, shape, or form of
existence you were risking the
spaces for all eternity
(Bell ringing)
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> next speaker.
>> welcome.
>> greetings supervisors and
hi to all the old supervisors
and welcome to the new
supervisors. I'm here today
representing the united alliance
tasking and we hand-delivered an
employer many of you received
this electronically about our
position calling and demanding a
hearing so thank you,
supervisors for allowing for
fouling
following up on that states of
emergencies when we rally and
take time to knock on our door
and get in our face it is not
person we need all the attention
for was happening in the
fillmore he and the places like
as walgreens is that hr c
dropped the ball in the form of
administration dropped the ball
and many supervisors have been
looking at this issue we're
trying to be nice but in being
nice we're trying to get results
and sometimes pains me that we
have to point out the sorry
about thats and all the things
that keep people away from the
city. However, the san
francisco redevelopment agency
answers to the 1956 decision
made by the board to take a
community and destroy a
community we want the facts we
want everybody to huddle
together and rebuild facts what
is going on behind the scenes
that deals that the fbi needs to
hear or people looking this
issue thank you for your
comments and wow.
>> before the next speaker.
>> you in the chamber hold our
applause we're happy you're here
by provide our silent approval
it would be nice thank you, sir
welcome.
>> welcome.
>> to the new and old
supervisors and you can push
that button and sit do you thing
this is person very person how
to justify failure and have a
serious lung disease right now
are the state of the emergency
even when the actions of good
faith were going out you have
the air in the building and the
fillmore center and got the
railroad building and ellis and
now we've got faith and all that
being done I appreciate you
supervisor for calling the
hearing when you call the
hearing that is tearing us apart
I'm fighting for 3 cities my
children is about time we stop
pussy footing around and put
together a hearing for the
future and safeway with the 50
year commitment to now lease it
that's what we want to do fine
here's my problem when you do
that and don't-anybody has to
talk with them, no negotiations
tapping we were left out of and
now here as a community 3
demanding an opportunity to be
involved with the negotiations
that our children's and
children's future and very
serious don't get in touch with
one person or a couple of people
(Bell ringing).
>> thank you, sir.
>> [Off mic.]
>> thank you sir.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> hear in the
next speaker.
>> good afternoon. I'm david
a resident of the city of san
francisco and been if the hayes
valley in district 5 and the
PRESIDENT Of hayes valley valley
association and my time here
today is specifically to welcome
and congratulate our supervisors
by to congratulate our new
district 5 supervisor mahmood
and his leadership and
background will be a welcomed
addition not only to the
neighborhood but I think for
this room. I like to
congratulate the new PRESIDENT
Of the board commissioner
mandelman last week you voted
him to be you're new PRESIDENT
In this room. And to me this
unanimous vote is encouraging
and suggested this board MAY
work together and despite police
ideas and differences which has
been long time coming and
unfortunately, mayor london
breed didn't get to enjoy that
luxurious luxury of working
together and under PRESIDENT
Mandelman and leaders our new
mayor will see a positive um, in
the neighborhoods throughout the
city. Please keep this practice
of working together and
throughout the term
(Bell ringing)
We're counting on all of you and
congratulations again on our
election.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> next speaker.
>> welcome.
>> supervisors. San francisco
was named after a saint and for
the kingdom of heaven. So your
supervisors who represent
resolutions need ordinances, we
need the charter. And do be mean
to the poor and homeless because
that's what I'm seeing on the
streets of san francisco. And
the walgreens made a lot of
money and I don't know how they
spent if we need quality of life
issues and not bullshit. Quality
of life issues and we need to
look after the elders and not
put them in the trailers and
don't need supervisors to be
involved in property management
didn't help with the management
we're watching you all and
shunned city hall 5 times in the
past. So it is not very
difficult to do it again. So
commissioner mandelman I know
you very well
(Bell ringing)
Your heart be in the right place
and only then can you take
others to a better place.
>> thank you welcome to the
next speaker.
>> my name is jim I'm a
partner of randy watching a
resident of laguna honda
hospital and is power of
attorney and yesterday, I attend
and health commission because
after years of couldn't have
done it without coinciding only
6 pages of a report that was
stacked 3 inches high was made
available to the public. Without
having read those reports, I can
assure you not just what was
reelevated in them not what was
not revealed I give testimony in
the public comment.
>> now the meeting for the
heat commissions are scheduling
on mondays the members of the
board can attend and encouraged
to attend for more clielgd has
happening at laguna honda I
thought not formed until laguna
honda was recertified.
Concerning safeway I got a
letter from safeway recommending
go to safeway because walgreens
was being closed
(Bell ringing).
>> thank you for your comments
and next speaker.
>> I'll I'm going to talk
really fast for all ladies and
gentlemen a serious problem. I'm
a strong ambassadorer in christ
and pay my family and
politicians. I came to our city
when I went to our shelters talk
about the drug problems. And
staff members are selling and I
saw a black women leave her
house upheld her 3 kids after
christmas all
[Off mic.]
>> why everybody's kids were
he home those women can't go
outside with the kids and play.
That is unreal it is wrong and
same thing with the shelters why
is there fentanyl and drugs and
needles and the people you hired
all you guys you should
understand
(Bell ringing).
>> you're selling. Supplying.
>> I come up and put cuffs on
me and said one 86 you're going
to jail.
>> why I got permission to
sleep by the station I stop
robberies and people that you're
going to jail james. Oh, I'm
going to take you to jail
twisted my arm I had to sign the
paperwork
(Bell ringing.)
>>
[Off mic.] Thank you for your
comments.
>> thank you for your
>> thank you for coming down
today and next speaker.
>> I want to start must
functional question we are
humans we see and-it is safe
to be a san franciscan. We
(Unintelligible) We have
$10 million how much of that
budget came from
(Unintelligible) PRESIDENT
Mandelman I remember you when
you were.
>> make our comments to the
board as a whole not to one
supervisor.
>> big deal.
>> be and team and housed I
mean-(Unintelligible).
>> jan invitation and what
kind of-and that do you
remember.
>> so my question PRESIDENT
Mandelman-the most
(Unintelligible).
>> very convenient to all
>> on the speed dial we need
to know.
>> you did say
(Unintelligible)
(Bell ringing)
Is it safe to be in san
francisco?
>> the other guy the day
support-also had to come to
the meeting.
>> that money must come to the
delegation we the public and-
need to know where money
(Unintelligible).
>> thank you for your comments
(Bell ringing)
Let's hear from the next
speaker.
>> please welcome.
>> good afternoon, supervisors
and the whole our new
supervisors I welcome you. My
name is-with the fillmore
united alliance. And thank you,
but what I'm hearing, of course,
walgreens and san francisco has
lasted to be a family city.
We're not driven as a family
city anymore but unfortunately,
mayor lee give benefits to the-
I think if we build san
francisco as a family city and
with the affordable housing with
the but with the economies we're
facing a safe way crisis in our
neighborhood; right? And before
safeway had had the fillmore
center trying to go
companionships but the fillmore
been on the chopping block since
the palm of west.
>> since the redevelopment
came our neighborhood; right?
And we've been through many
supervisors and many mayors the
last mayor congratulate her
coming to our community we
really need help in the fillmore
and need everyone in the city to
look at
(Bell ringing)
In our community; right? And as
we're on the eve of one black
man was ass that's martin luther
king and here fighting I want
you to take into consideration
we need the city all right. And
thank you for your comments.
>> let's hear from the next
speaker.
>> welcome.
>> my name is roy am victim of
a violent crime I want to show
you a picture I have pictures on
my right eye from living in a
center and got knocked to the
ground and coming in here asking
you guys to come to my rescue
and come to the district I have
come to the PRESIDENT
Congratulations but I'm a victim
of violent crime I can't fight
you guys by mitch I have
injuries life threatening
injuries and my insurance
company will not cover my
insurance and I'm having serious
medical problems and I coming
here asking you guys to come in
many times I mean the district I
live in don't come to my rescue
where due go you want me to kick
the violence with my own hand
the the charges against the city
employees you must supervisor or
because they're covering up I
show they're covering up a
violent crime with the employees
(Unintelligible). Thank you.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> welcome and my name is
definitely la and welcome to you
hope you contribute in doing a
better job in what has happened
in the past two years I'm the
social justice fighter for my
people and culture and going to
be passing out MADAM Secretary.
>> it is to verify that I am
the reason that bayview-hunters
point I'm the founder and
creator of the african person
that to bring the culture into
the bay area and am the founder
and creator and former it was
made because of my sacrificing
my life for the city of san
francisco and the gold
represented my son was murdered
in san francisco in what quad
draubl handled I fought for two
years to get a trial it just
happened as far as 4 or 5 weeks
ago and lee was the only
survivor and charged with four
accounts and the board of
supervisors can't say he is the
contribution to make sure a
remembering my son-I want to
read this formation
(Bell ringing).
>> if I can separating ours of
the typical african-american and
coming to you with the tribal
law will give us represent
practitioner and
(Bell ringing)
My goal over and over.
>> thank you time is concluded.
>> thank you kindly.
>> thank you, MS. Chandler.
>> thank you.
>> welcome our.
>> next speaker, please.
>> members of board of
supervisors I have had the
principle to work with you, we
can get on first family basis
I'm proud of come a long way.
>> let me say we as the people
can get to the promise land. You
can't do it by ourselves I can't
do that by my self but allow the
race to become e tint culture is
the best success foreman kind
once I have no culture no
history no past. Therefore the
same mistakes will happen over
and over and over again.
>> imagine los angeles right
now. Look at the buyers they're
out. That is what the fillmore
has become. You can't allow
people to be wrong you if you're
going to the mlk mark and walk
down that street
(Bell ringing).
>> unions and everybody else
have an obligation to be an
american this is the united
states of america. This is for
all of us when we suffer you
suffer. And mlk breakfast I want
to let you know that DR. Richard
amy's brown was honored at the
mlk breakfast
(Bell ringing).
>> this is the kind of work.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> thank you.
>> hear from the next speaker.
>> please.
Welcome.
>> hello.
>> first of all,
congratulations to the new
supervisors and the PRESIDENT Of
the board PRESIDENT Mandelman is
we're going to see a lot of good
things in 2020 I'm PRESIDENT Of
the neighborhood soccer in
district 2 that borders safeway
on the-and the co-chair the
van ness coalition and covers my
supervisors districts we're
concerned about the closure of
this safeway without any
discussion? Input, about any
short term plan and long term
plan and any community
involvement and very anxious to
avert the redevelopment where
things are demolished and torn
down with the security issue we
like to see from safeway before
in sale is concluded a plan for
the businesses a construction
plan, a proposal that will go in
there and cooperation with
speaking with the communities
all around and transportation
and other departments we want to
look forward to it. Thank you.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> next speaker, please.
>> >> good afternoon.
>> I wanted to welcome all the
new supervisors we're happy
you're representing the
district. I'm alice I'm from
district 5 and I wanted to thank
supervisors for coming into the
community the other day. None of
you no that is a culture food
and, you know, food for us to
all your cultures is very
important. And with the safeway
intending closure in FEBRUARY we
are really calling this an
emergency because not only the
western addition and fillmore
not only japantown but all the
sensor community and have to
make sure that everyone gets
nutrition they have access to
medication and they can do if
without walking miles and miles
this week this is the state of
emergency I brought it up at the
meeting we were outside at the
press conference those folks
stayed around to go to almost
every supervisors office he tell
you what has been done and we're
(Bell ringing)
Looking to help us figure out to
feed the people more importantly
and keep us safe. Thank you.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> welcome to the next
speaker.
>> good afternoon.
>> my name is fong and proud
to be a fourth generation
groundwater grandfather came in
1903 and had the honor of se as
a staffer to the human rights
commission in 1983. And so I've
retired 7 years ago but very
active no community and I come
upon an important time for
PRESIDENT Mandelman got to know
each other way what can. And if
you hear the new supervisors I
welcome you, we need he
everyone's help to work together
and volunteering we are one and
like to see this board of
supervisors come in walking egg
both we're one to pack our city
better again like we can be more
powderer than we are.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> welcome to the next
speaker.
>> I'm larry a co-founder of
the unit group here in san
francisco and also a college
student at san francisco state I
want to share that, you know, we
jaw now entering 2025 I hope and
pray each of you take advantage
of the opportunity you have
because I believe in universal
calling and best to invest in
the people
struggling that don't have I
know everyone ask talking about
the middle
llion airs and bill
arrests and take from people in
the best interest of you to pass
bills and invest in the
community not take away lucky
the fillmore this is had
consequences I pray for my
brothers and sisters in
california and pray for san
francisco I hope you make the
right decisions the decision you
all make is actually life and
death. You know what I hope
you're serious about the
policies and is decision you all
make that is what you are
dealing with life and if you're
not taking life you need to
reconsider. Thank you.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> welcome to the next
speaker.
>> good afternoon
congratulations to all in the
coming supervisors I'm karen
citizen of integrity 5 and
member of the st. Francis
cooperative and here with my
neighbors to demand action on
the the culture of safeway. As
supposed of late stage
californiaism and the robbery
bearing takes office we expand
the larger of martin luther king
I ask to look at his work
capitalism in a few weeks on our
watch and vast food desert and
services capital management and
new york private firm with
$60 billion the fillmore is not
around for neighbors in wash and
western addition and japantown
the safeway is lifeline this
lifeline is cut the heart and
soul will bleed out and seniors
and working families on tight
budget and everyday people like
my neighbors in st. Francis will
go hunger and spend time
traveling grocery stores and it
is look forward to imagine the
developer will not build for
years. The majority of our board
of supervisors will support from
neighbors for a better san
francisco together
(Bell ringing)
And grow sf and none of those
represent the organizations
they're funded by billionaires
and fooled by and handout of
white people with a golden
police department to keep the
people from rising up we
encourage you to go to those
organizations and work with us
create and community trust and
by the fillmore site to select a
intervening
(Bell ringing).
>> thank you for your comments
comments.
>> welcome.
>> welcome all the new
supervisors I will say this is-
my name is ace I'm on the case
and been here 5 administrations
and been around. Not as long as
willie brown but been around.
>> I'm here to relate to the
new supervisors that we have a
very state of emergency in 5
districts I'm in the fillmore. I
will be going out my program
rolling out my program and-but
here to testify of this new
administration supervisors. And
must petition to all the people
saying because this is going to
be your work. And I'm looking
forward to meeting all of you
welcome I call if you call it
city hall I call it silly hall
so the thing I want to explain
we're in a new era have no time
for errors misguided leadership
and all effort and egregious
undermining our community not
standing for that and recognize
and bring do we hope will get
help to all the speakers that
came today
(Bell ringing)
Supervisors and even the mayor's
office so we're doing a good job
of this generation of leadership
a new beginning and we're invite
all people
watching to join with us we're
going fighting for our community
and children and children,
children children.
>> my name is ace I'm on the
case you'll see me every tuesday
because I have (Unintelligible)
(Bell ringing)
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> welcome to the next
speaker.
>> good afternoon my name is
leonard the MR. Lubelski of the
special police officers training
and also live in the same house
that my mom and dad built and
too officers in the fillmore the
church, I go to I have an office
there and am purchasing that
building at 1807 folsom street
for the academy and so forth and
members tuesday is our meeting
night as well but I want to
share with you some things
because I grew up in the
fillmore and but I came back
from the military I thought the
war was in the fillmore. All the
lots were empty and all were
torn up and I would like to put
a carnival an fillmore street
and when I walked around with
the carnival you can't put it
here and there and not going
into any black neighborhood to
put on an carnival but part of
police commission and any
teacher had officers to the
fillmore we put on a carnival
(Bell ringing)
We've helped quite a few people
in the transition from crime or
whatever else to life. And some
of the members might speak on
this how we helped them in the
last 50 years I want to share
that is difficult we or doing
that and we'll be back here
again, thank you.
>> thank you, sir, for your
comments. Welcome to the next
speaker.
>>
(Bell ringing)
>> welcome you good MISS.
>> my name is kenny robinson
and I'm a trainee for a special
police officers association and
first time coming to this
building period and hear some of
my intents. I just came here I
would like to come down with my
chief to submit some of the
wires among our staff what we
provide and what we're trying to
do and to promote some kind of
funding for our program. To um,
keep us established been stacey
that for 61 years now and for me
been a new lifestyle than way
used to side a x felon and now
want to transform to every
structure and embrace myself
with community. I more or less
want to work with my staff to
promote our
(Bell ringing)
Training academy we are getting
up that is 6 and a half years
compared to the lifestyle I
served if prison and 15 years of
freedom without incident working
with the academy is helped me
allowed me to replace myself in
communities and society and more
productive. So I just came down
here
(Bell ringing)
-
>> thank you, sir, for coming
down here this governor thank
you for your comments.
>> see you in two weeks ago
and hear from the.
>> next speaker, please.
>> >> housing my name is
mark alexander. And been here
for a little bit over 2 years
now and you know san francisco
is a very interesting place
complex politics. So regards the
safeway um, I think that san
francisco has failed the
fillmore district. And we can't
handle any more failures in the
future you was telling the
supervisors not just on you but
all of san francisco city to
solve this problem. Um, and
that's all I have to say I'm a
little bit nervous right now.
>> thank you for your comments
this afternoon next speaker.
>> please.
And good evening. I'm jeffrey
I'm part of s po a police
officers association and
NOVEMBER 1997 I committed a
crime that was murder and spent
22 years in prison. We needed
funding at 1807 postal street
been locked up a long time and
out only 4 years and recidivism
is a big thing every time I come
up here I don't know what will
happen happen and this is my
third time speaking this is me
letting you know I conditional
use permit this crime and
recidivism at 1807 I'll do that
until I get it I'm jeffrey am on
1807 on folsom street and
getting training askinging
asking you guys to greet the
brochures I'll be looting my
person belonging if I reach out
but letting I know that we will
keep on coming and do until you
guys look at us I'm jeffrey you
guys have a great everything.
Thank you. Jeffrey thank you for
your comments. Welcome to the
next speaker.
>> hello my name is a dustin.
I'm representing intersection 08
and I'm nervous. I was homeless
for 18 months before that and in
and out of jails for the last 18
years and have is a place to
stay and have a chance to better
myself everyday and help thanks.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> let's hear in the next
speaker welcome.
>> hi, my name is lopez.
>> I'm part of sp 08.
>> to here to ask for this
organization and ask the
supervisors to do something
about that with us and hoping we
can embrace um, wiling our
communities and we
(Unintelligible). Thank you.
>> thank you for your
comments thank you for coming
down this afternoon and welcome
to the next speaker.
>> >> good morning. I'm
josephine and congratulations
supervisor chan and supervisor
sauter and supervisor mahmood
and all for your election
congratulations PRESIDENT
Mandelman. We look forward to
working with you. I ask you to
please keep the great highway
open and up-to-date emergency
plan can be worked out also
think excavation to the water
system the emergency gate
opening fell over two
earthquakes in a week don't want
a-my family and in laws and
cousins and aunts are all in the
sunset we need subversions I'm
looking at I I'm going to make
19 you accountability for my
life lost.
>> thank you.
>> thank you for your comments
reverend A.M. Must brown
welcome.
>> MR. CHAIRMAN
(Bell ringing)
>> members of the board of
supervisors, especially to those
of you who are joining this
brown patch. I'm sure you know
who I am. I served on this
board. And sat there wondering
waiting after having heard
persons speak from the debts of
their hearts with clarity of
thought and appealing to our
will not just listen. But to see
us. And to do something. I have
been coming to this body for
half
half a century a sad commentary
saying san francisco didn't like
black folks if it did that would
wouldn't have done what happened
in the fillmore or given them if
you have information in the
negotiation times when they
wrote an article blacks with
made to feel lonely in san
francisco I'm sure I saw that
movie the blast black man in san
francisco. That not cutting you
off but please, please pretty
please let us get a new skin
stop committing again and again
saying the crime against the
humanity of black people
(Bell ringing)
Safeway got away. And time for
us to put the brakes on. And to
say that all lists will not
turnover one spade of dirt for
this ground they're on they
stole it through safeway who got
to. Below the value. Safeway
lived because black folks died
figuratively speaking
(Bell ringing)
MADAM Chair, who presided over
is finance committee I remember
when you gave that report you're
response on reparations you said
I'm sorry this board cried
crocodile tears said sorry about
the injustices and against black
folks we don't have no money.
Well, that's to be considered.
But remember how aaron peskin
suggested to this body if we
don't have money we should adopt
problematic and I submit this
afternoon that that holy ground
what safeway is should be a part
of reparations and make sure the
harris building is declared a
horrifying lark because the
children gave the books on this
ground. Why? Because DR.
Benjamin whose name on the
street out here his office is
there. Why the same area my
agile was a workshop why the
third baptist church. The
redevelopments agency played
games and said no housing but
the constitution and commercial
use of whether MR. Petition
changed the rules in the middle.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> what we're left with now as
I end thank you, ma'am clerk for
hearing me this average of time
to stop analyzing we thank you
for the hearing MR. Supervisor
but must not make this thing on
a pharmacies of an analysis if
we're in the city of st. Francis
and knows how to do the right
thing let's get this-just do
it and stop all the talk.
>> and give black folks their
dignity in this town then we
will indeed be a place where
believing every human heart is
in san francisco.
>> thank you reverend brown.
>> any other members of the
public want to address the
board.
>> step up.
>> I'm ken a native san
franciscan and been dealing with
city hall since-mayors and you
all know what happened to the
fillmore. You know the history.
All we are asking for is you've
taken everything from the
fillmore and just think about
that. Now you want to take the
safeway have the power in our
hands to help rebuild the fill
more and help us, we want to
bring back the um, tourism and
want to make help the city, you
know, be a shining light we want
tourists to come to fillmore we
bring back. We want our
community to sparlg. I mean you
this city has taken all of the
pride out of the people in
fillmore we still have we have
hope. And we have so many talent
there and want to fill more
heritage center opened up that
is totally ridiculous you never
let the people under the
fillmore operate it and no
further let the people there
operate it. That's all we ask is
fairness that's it.
>> thank you next speaker.
>> welcome.
>> good evening good
afternoon. I'm dra us and I'm
representing the security this
is two important topics they
concern me and others like me.
Sp 08 started 50 years ago and
as a speaker before me said san
francisco has a rich and
cultural I'm from oakland and
been in the training center for
three years.
>> um, I make no excuses
because I'm an "x" felony let
you know that right off the bat.
All of those crimes were
committed over 17 and 20 years
ago and last time I was in
prison was 2005 and last time in
the county jail was 2009 in my
search for recovery and
extensively betterment I found
the security that carters to x
offenders like myself they don't
have the funding for a proper
recidivism program
(Bell ringing)
And the city of san francisco
has the fund to allocate. And
I'm just lost as to why it is.
>> um, p sp 08 is a san
francisco run program we for
everyone and some of my
coworkers in the audience today
and represent many.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> thank you for coming down
this afternoon
(Bell ringing)
>> I'm sorry, sir everyone is
allocated two minutes and have a
large agenda to get to and
individuals to get in the
audience.
>> thank you, sir. Thank you,
kindly next speaker.
>> and if there are any other
members of the public would like
to address the board step up or
this is the last speaker and
welcome, sir.
>> good afternoon. My name is
I'm a taxi driver for $2,250
when I left india and an
american architect. The most
beautiful city in india and live
in fremont I moved to tracey and
4 miles can you believe it as
shameful.
>> living in the village with
paying $250 to the city and any
taxi was stolen by lyft and uber
and the city has given you-
died in the columbia 2003.
>> (Unintelligible).
>> and other familiar attorney
had dillon-to the assistant of
attorney general for these human
rights. So we need we don't make
no money we take less money home
(Bell ringing)
I have invest and coming up with
seven years to city hall and no
one cares and don't care about
the family my children-don't
have a chance to go because I
can't afford to pay the colleges
and decided to go to.
>> staff recommends approval.
Of /-
sfusd.
>> thank you, sir. Your time is
conducted.
>> now you're taken advantage
of of this. Thank you.
[Off mic.]
>> thank you.
>> let's hear from the next
speaker welcome, sir.
>> thank you board.
>> too bad my name is-
>> and the reason why I am
here today is because of
safeway. And the way that we
have been done in the fillmore
area. I came-I came here for a
better life. But behold it
didn't get any better. You know,
why?
>> because we as people still
(Unintelligible) It is time,
time is winding down. And we
should come together help one
another. Do not like color get
away from that I've been on-I
have been on hospital piece I
have 8 diseases but I get up and
fight I'll also fight for my
people because my people didn't
come here on their own they were
born here. So they are therefore
open your eyes and look around
and see what is going to happen.
And we'll be destroyed if we
don't work together.
>> thank you for your
comments.
>> any other members of the
public who lee would like to
address the board during general
public comment.
>> MR. PRESIDENT.
>> thank you, MADAM Clerk >>
let's go to the.
>> MR. PRESIDENT please close
public comment.
>> public comment is closed.
>> let's go
>> let's go to
replacement projects in certain
buildings;affirming the planning
department's determination under
the california environmental
quality act and findings. You
colleagues anyone want to sever
any of the items?
>> I do for the see anyone in
the queue. So MADAM Clerk could
you please MADAM Clerk, call the
roll.
>> >> on items 20 and 21,
supervisor chan, aye.
>> supervisor dorsey, aye.
>> and supervisor engardio,
aye.
>> supervisor fielder, aye.
>> supervisor mahmood, aye.
>> new mexico.
>> aye.
>> supervisor melgar, aye.
>> supervisor sauter see, aye.
>> and supervisor sherrill,
aye.
>> supervisor walton, aye.
>> supervisor chan.
>> there are 11, aye.
>> and approved item 21 and
past telephone public comment
call the special order 2:30 P.M.
-recognition of commendations.
>> >>
>> >> item.
>> 2. Hearing of the board of
supervisors sitting as a
committee of the whole, on
JANUARY 14, 2025, at 3:00 P.M.
To hold a public hearing to
consider 15 urgent accept and
expend resolutions, authorizing
the port of san francisco,
department of public
works,department of environment,
department of public health,
recreation and park
government in various amounts
and for variety of purposes and
projects; scheduled pending
approval of the motion and
findings. Excuse me-
findings. Excuse me-number.
>> committee of the whole
adjourn and report: item nos. 3
through 17 shall require an
affirmative vote of eight
members of the board due to the
suspension of board rule 2.8 and
clerk of the board process and
policies that mandate all
documents be submitted and
municipal code requirements met
prior to board consideration.
Emergency services for the pier
94/96 seismic improvement
project for the period of
JANUARY 31, 2025, through AUGUST
4, 2027.
Office of emergency services to
establish an engineering with
nature working group for the
period of JANUARY 31, 2025,
through MARCH 12, 2027.
DECEMBER 31,
and target and deliver technical
assistance to disadvantaged
communities; retroactively
approving the grant agreement
and findings.
And findings.
>> 6. Resolution authorizing
the department of the
environment ("
environment
department"
) To accept and
expend a grant award of up to
$284,800 for the period from
APRIL 1, 2025, to MARCH 31,
2027, from the united states
department of energy, to hire a
new community engagement liaison
(Cel) Position for two years to
support energy and environmental
-
participation in a program,
entitled "
state vocational
rehabilitation services
program,"
for the period of
JULY 1, 2025, through JUNE 30,
calendar year 2025, from the
united states department of
transportation, federal highway
administration for the
development and deployment of
development and deployment of-
program entitled "
calaim ji path
round 2 funding-san
francisco,"
for the period of
MAY 26, 2023, through
OCTOBER 31,
bicycle and pedestrian safety
improvement project for grant
performance period from grant
contract execution through
AUGUST 30,
department of transportation to
fund the bayview connections:
phase 1 harney way bus rapid
transit (Brt) And cycletrack
project, 12 through 17 are
called from xae to be considered
in a program, entitled "
refugee
support services (Rss) Funding-
san francisco,"
for the period
of OCTOBER 1, 2023,through
SEPTEMBER 30, 2026.
Twin peaks promenade project,
for a grant performance period
from SEPTEMBER 20, 2024, through
MARCH 15,
amount of $1,212,299 for a total
grant amount of $13,635,302 from
the centers for disease control
and prevention for participation
in a program, entitled
"
strengthening std prevention
and control for health
departments (Std pchd),"
for the
period of JANUARY 1, 2019,
through FEBRUARY 28, 2026.
Through FEBRUARY 28, 2026.
>> 15. Resolution retroactively
authorizing the department of
public health to accept and
expend grant increase in the
amount of $13,431 from the
national institutes of health
through the university of texas
southwestern medical center, for
a new total amount of $104,508
for
protection agency (Epa), to fund
the san francisco waterfront
emissions-free ferry system for
the period of JANUARY 1, 2025,
through DECEMBER 31, 2028.
>> all right. Thank you,
MADAM Clerk.
>> colleagues the purpose of
this committee of the whole to
vote on a package of 15.
>> (Speaking foreign language.)
Amounting to more than one
hundred and $33 million. Those
items represent the federal fund
by 6 departments given the
change in the federal government
it is wise to doing everything
we can to bring down the funds
as quickly as potential
potential go for the
recommendation and thereafter,
come to the full board here's is
majority if we're agreeable
prior to the considerations of
their expenditure, however,
those funds once secured will be
held in the board reserve. And
in terms in terms of the board
that preserving this and the
approval of those items
captioned will require and super
majority and today hearing from
each of the 6 departments that
is the department of environment
and port and putting and public
works and the rec and park and
the human services agency the
grants are 5 of million dollars
for the port for $20 million for
the rapid transit and
$20 million for the energy
reduction in the buildings with
benefits and $15 million for the
employment of electrical
vehicles and one $.6 million for
the crises and 18 thousand for
the get-togethers and more for
the transit built improvements
and lark park upgrades and
healthcare for the population
and seismic upgrades throughout
the city and the departments
will give in their presentations
but first recognize the steroid
effort going on in getting those
items for today and first of
all, thank our clerk our deputy
clerk and team and the clerk's
office super quickly and corral
all the departments that made
this submit all the things they
needed to submit and been a big,
big lift and want to thank you
for that and thank eileen in the
mayor's office past, present,
and future work on this last
last week and more acknowledges
with the department.
>> (Calling names.)
>> and floated this idea and
were the drivers that made this
happen and executive director
eileen and carla short and
others and director DR. DR.
Colfax from the department of
putting and the filling ginsburg
and.
>> (Calling names.)
>> greg wagner, controller and
my staff and lots and caps for
harder thank you, colleagues
thank you for your consideration
and thank supervisor chan for
your work with the
administration I know you have
one item you'll talk about now
and one of those items to the
legislation and supervisor chan.
>> thank you new mexico and
wendy concur with the sentiment
of urgency especially give in
light of what our southern
california counterparts are
dealing with and federal support
and yet having haitians and
difficulties. So it is with
recognize that with urgency we
must extend those grant provided
by our federal agencies. With
the exception colleagues, I want
to ask for your support to refer
this to the committee the button
committee the reason we were
given those items clearly are in
need of urgent approval we
recognize item 10 is a state
grant and a lot of effort so
share the gratitude that and
express-wanted to also just
thank MR. Adams from the mayor's
office for the collaboration
that we've think working on and
maybe just like for him to
quickly confirm that the mayor's
office is in support of this
action referring back to the
budget committee.
>> through the chair. Thank
you, supervisor chan and that
change is for the mayor's
office.
>> there's a motion we can
vote on that now.
>> motion do I have a second?
>> MR. PRESIDENT no, we need
to take public comment and is
there a second?
>> seconded by and we have a
motion and a second. We'll deal
with that after the public
comment.
>> so alright with that,
director chiu.
>> good afternoon, supervisors
with the environmental depth I
want to echo my thanks to
PRESIDENT Mandelman and this was
a collaboration truly began in
NOVEMBER we released the clock
was ticking we saw that was
happening from the federal
government over the past months
rapid rolling out grants in that
week to get to this point in
front of the board all those
individuals and tremendous
amount of thinking outside the
box but the clerk on our team
alicia and everyone that made
this possible for k. And I'll be
going over this item for the
environmental department and
answer any questions. So we have
a presentation.
>>-number 5?
>> okay. Item 5.
>> um, item 5 is the inflation
reduction act and the energy for
14 approximately $3 million is
allocated for the city of san
francisco and the remaining to
the city of berkley for the
grants application that we
submitted. And the reason we did
this we want to not only
decarbonize the building in the
locations but create an index
replicated through the the
bayview and throughout the
nation and specifically the
grants award will fund both the
technical staff and work
required to bring everyone to
develop the policy and bring
this policy back to the braid
for consideration at a future
date and if the fund passes. The
second item item 6 is for a
clean city community engagement
liaison that is funded through
the department of energy the 200
and $84,000 plus the creation of
a
an itemy
a temporary position for the
outreach for the electrical
vehicles adoption. And the last
and
this grant will fund up to three
hundred level 2 or g c parts in
san francisco and put 80 percent
towards the installing of
charging electrical vehicles by
2030 and focusing on the equity
community identified and this
grant will help to fund the
curbside charging programs for
the commercial and multi-family
residential areas. And with
that, I'll be happy to answer
any questions you MAY have.
>> before I'm I'm going to turn
it over to public
>> members of the public MAY
address the commission on
matters that are within the
commission's jurisdiction
supervisor fielder I'm glad to
see is department raise these
grants important for us to
expedite this reduction as a
huge win for the environmental
justice folks across the
country. And I just so grateful
to the department to take the
time to bring this before the
board and the mayor's office.
Thank you.
>> thank you.
>> all right.
>> with that, thank you,
director chiu and let's hear
from public works.
>> good afternoon PRESIDENT
Mandelman and supervisors
echoing the gratitude I'd like a
project manager with public
works and today be presenting
item item 11 the award from the
department of transportation for
the bay area project.
>> and also joined by the
candle stake folks and hear to
answer any questions.
>> the public works awarded
$20 million for the rebuilding
for the infrastructure with the
sustainability and raised
program and the bay area project
is part of a candle stick for
the larger redevelopment plan to
get upgrade. And improving the
accessibility to employment and
activity center creating and
walkable site and the grants
includes widening the extending
portion of harvey and widened
sidewalks and the candle dell
stick contributes $26 million
for the wall of project and
public works is work together to
complete the design and
subdivision and construction
programs in the next year and
seeks to authorize for the
implementation of grant thank
you for your time and I'll be
happy to answer any questions
you MAY have.
>> but we don't have questions
let's hear in the port.
>> good afternoon, supervisors
I'm the san francisco government
affairs manager and 3
resolutions before you today.
The first is item number 3, on
the agenda from the federal
emergency management. Or brick
this grant will fund the
engineering nature working group
for the nature based solution
for the projects related to our
waterfront and this working
group will be from the army corp
of engineers and the others and
final report will be provided
that with integrate that lion
with the brick funding essential
and building a map to win future
refunding opportunities the
grant is valued at one hundred
and $60,000 roughly and requires
an 80 thousand match. Our second
grant is item number 3, on your
agenda I referred to item 3.
This is also in the federal
management agency this time
through they're hazard mediation
grant program pier 94 and 96
with the
with the for cargo and maritime
use a critical deepwater
maritime for the the pier was
due to slop flavors and damage
makes it unusable for the
activities and in AUGUST we won
a $2.7 million grant and so
assess and have a report and
prepare the documents up to 60
per completion for the
environmental approvals to begin
in-this is a project with a
.32 month duration and requires
$900,000.
>> our third grant is we're
excited about item 17 on the
agenda the administration though
the inflation reduction act
created the clean hearts program
to reduce the utilization. In
OCTOBER the port along with sf
ferry to public utilities
commission and the working
waterfront conclusion to fund
the first high ferry network in
the united states this project
about support 4 key consultants
they are the construction for
the ferry landing across the
street from the center and the
flip of the new bay front park
and the electrification and
vision zero for high speed rail
ferry and the workforce program
totals $53 million and is a
$53 million match and of the the
match some is coming from hetch
hetchy power decision to build
the underground structure for
the ferry terminal and the
remaining one.8 is coming from
sf ferry we looked at to working
with you and the impact report
and the finance committee we're
grateful to mayor-elect daniel
lurie and PRESIDENT Mandelman
team and the office to expedite
this approval forward and
joining by megan and we're
available to answer any
questions.. Thank you for your
time.
>> thank you. I 82 on you
answered the questions with the
public help.
>> good afternoon merry relay
chief financial officer and
grateful to be here and bringing
4 grants for our review starting
with number 7 for the employment
services for adults serious
mental health and the department
of education through the
california departments the how
many amount and the timeline
from JULY 25th through JUNE of
28 and so the grant will be
performed for the cooperative
contracts through 5 nonprofits
including richmond and citywide
case management and the programs
for the. That was item 7.
>> next item for us item
number 14. So this grant
entitled std prevention and
really a core funding for the
prevention control. Whoops.
>> so the goal of this grant
to conduct the disease
investigation and strengthen the
response and limitation to
prevention and treatment. And
case management for hiv and
sexually transmitted disease
current 5 years starred in
JANUARY of 19 and runs through
FEBRUARY of 26 the the
specific
bringing the total to 13.
>> the increase will be used
to the goals of the funding and
maintain combrefrns next item is
15. This is a grant entitled
clinical from nih through texas
and the grants is part of a the
big southwest of the clinical
trials a research network in the
fat I forget a national
institute within nih for the
research and determine the
efficiency of the extended
release of medication. Compared
to move forward the injects for
the same use of cocaine and the
grants increase represents a
$13,000 increase bringing the
total to one hundred and 4
households will be MARCH 24th
through 2025 and this grants is
extensive opioid substance abuse
site based program to the
department of justice and the
goal to create an overdose
review with with the office of
the overdose review team are
review overdose and increase
identifying the ways to
prevention overdose. The total
amount one $.6 million and the
grants if OCTOBER 2024 through
SEPTEMBER 27th.
>> thank you.
>> thank you, MR. Morale no
questions hear from the next
department.
>> good afternoon board of
supervisors and commissioner
mandelman.
>> beverly with rec and park
provide you a little bit of
background in SEPTEMBER of 2024
we were awarded from the federal
highway administration and they
do the rec and park for the
promenade we are panning to go
out to bid in the end of JANUARY
and construction in light summer
of 2025 we look forward to
having this go through and thank
you to the mayor's office and
the board and for moving this as
quickly as possible a bringing
promenade allowing the folks for
open space and all the wonderful
stuff. Thank you.
>> thank you. Years any
questions? Let's hear under the
major services committee.
>> good afternoon.
>> MR. PRESIDENT and board
members I'm the budget director
for the human resources I'm here
to present the two items under
our agency item 9 and 12 so the
first item number 9 respectfully
requesting your approval of an
and we've been to process
medi-cal for just individuals
when they're out transitioning
in to be transition into
incarceration and back, back
into the community.
>> as you can see the
population in prison individuals
often face significant social
challenges and chronic health
conditions and substance abuse
issues and a lack of housing or
employment. This grant was
awarded by the california
department of healthcare and was
included in the package and was
made possible via and
demonstration project with the
federal funding from the federal
human services agency and
overall the obviously the award
is 200 and $23,000 plus and
available to conservatives
through OCTOBER 1st of 24 and
the proceed to the next item.
>> so our next item is number
12 on the agenda. Here we're
MRS. Rrnltd asking for the
retroactive of a refugee support
service this award was made by
the federal officer. Made polk
for the federal officer of
refugee resettlement and totals
$800,000 plus be used for
supportive services through you
2016 and will fund 3 areas
employment and housing
assistance and connect refugees
to a variety of benefits. And in
particular those we need to the
agency directly administer lice
cal w and calfresh and refugee
employment services overall this
will help refugees achieve and
maintain how to stabilize and
ultimately zath into the life
into sharing communities in san
francisco. And lastly, just add
that while it is uncommon what
changes maybe forth coming to
the federal refugee funding
resources the approval of this
grant helps us to maximize this
for populations that we believe
will be severely under serviced
in the new administration
I'm available for any questions
that you MAY have.
>> um, I'll confess I have
reon one hand if those need
board of supervisors approval
but given our rules currently
require that we come to a why is
long on these looks like they
were grand if 2023.
>> sure the first one cal am
the reason why we're seeking
retroactive approval of the
project is intended to fund a 16
mow period and built in the
first 12 months in the budget
but submitted the additional
funding this year.
>> (Multiple voices).
>> for the budget.
>> yes.
>> okay. And oh, you-
>> (Multiple voices).
>> next question. The second
one this is a reoccurring grants
we received and the an
additional work order good news
we proclaimed them but the award
that came to us was suggesting
large we received this award
around 11 thousand and it was 16
that is good news we're
requesting it to get in program
this year and spend the money
before the contract grant
expires.
>> thank you.
>>. Thank you.
>> so I think that is the
that's it everybody.
>> so we MAY go to public
comment.
>> MADAM Clerk.
>> is there anyone in the
chambers this afternoon like to
address the board regarding the
committee of the whole and items
3 through 17 will please step up
to the podium.
>> all right. MR. PRESIDENT.
>> great.
>> um, public comment is
closed.
And I actually have-
>> this concludes the
committee of the whole hearing
and now declare hearing is heard
and filed and MADAM Clerk we've
already you've called-
>> (Multiple voices).
>> MAY I ask you to gavel down
to make sure.
>> the hearing is filed and so
and you already called item 3 to
17 and-but have to do things
for each of the items to accept
them and, of course, have
particulars and get to 10. But I
think the way and I MADAM Clerk
you'll restate each item as we
get to that and I'll provide a
summary of the amendments the
amendments for board members I
think you have the packets
summarizes them but read into
the record is that; correct.
>> yes. MR. PRESIDENT.
>> all right. You want to
take it away with item
94/96 seismic improvement
project for the period of
JANUARY 31, 2025, through
AUGUST 4, 2027. >> okay.
>> so hear the amendments on 7
through 10 and those
determination for the la with
the finish line impact and 14
and 15 for the deergs that was
received and staff report is not
required and on page 3 line 56
properly identify project
assurance for federal assistance
is there a motion to accept the
amendment. Do I have a second?
>> seconded by supervisor chan
and then I think without
objection these amendments can
be approved.
(Gavel).
>> any on the resolution as
amended.
>> same house, same call.?
>> without objection the
resolution as amended is adopted
and MADAM Clerk, call the next
item, please.
>>
office of emergency services to
establish an engineering with
nature working group for the
period of JANUARY 31, 2025,
through MARCH 12, 2027.
>> okay. So on the amendments
here on page 2 line 8 through 9
we are striking the reference to
the he pending impact
determination for the la
determines not-on page 2 line
13 and 14 sdeermz no finish line
impact and to identify the
agreement for the board 30 years
project assurance for federal
assistance and then on page 3
line 3 through 4 reference to
the impact reminders for la
determines no impact and claire
the file will be reviewed and is
there a motion to accept the
amendments as proposed.
>> moved by supervisor dorsey
and seconded by supervisor
walton and then we can take ass
amendments without objection
they were approved and own the
resolution amend take these.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection the resolution
as amended is adopted.
(Gavel)
And MADAM Clerk, call the next
item, please.
>> 7 or 5 you
>> 7 or 5 you a 5.
>> >> 5. Resolution
retroactively authorizing the
department of the environment
("
environment department"
) To
accept and expend a grant award
of $19,994,217 for the period
from JANUARY 1,
energy, office of state and
community energy programs (Scep)
For the development,
>> okay.
>> (Clapping.)
(Clearing throat)
My groaning will continue we're
striking reference to the
pending impact determines and
this matter didn't have finish
line impact and line 21 updating
no finish line impact on page 4
clarifying that the file will be
reviewed for completion and line
5 MADAM Clerk no position should
be funded by the grant unless
approved in the future and
positions shall be-and
considered with the file.
>> and is there a motion to
accept the motion by supervisor
chan and seconded by supervisor
chen and motion we have a motion
and a second. Without objection
those amendments are approved
(Gavel).
>> off.
>> want to make a quick
remark.
>> oh, sorry.
>> so PRESIDENT Mandelman and
I colleagues particular for the
new members I think for the
application of rile what the 8
sp sailor ordinance it is
critical to have this amendment
not just a accept and expend
we're creating and position a
salary position that requires
someone to administer those
grants and that as we continue
to move forward as a city and
thinking about our deficit
something for us to think about
when we accept the grants means
that he remember maybe in need
of hiring anyone new and what do
we do in the position for for
the longs haul and especially
with the grant runs out and the
position should no longer exist
but need an ongoing position
when the grant expires and
thanks to the mayor's office and
the city partners being able to
be allow us working together to
have an amendment is critical I
want to express that sentiment
and emigrates manner of doing
this typically we don't do so
thank you very much and I'm in
sports of those amendments.
>> thank you supervisor chen
for clarify and I believe motion
was made without objection this
resolution is adopted
(Gavel).
>> MADAM Clerk next item,
please.
>> 6. Resolution authorizing
the department of the
environment ("
environment
department"
) To accept and
expend a grant award of up to
$284,800 for the period from
APRIL 1, 2025, to MARCH 31,
2027, from the united states
department of energy, to hire a
new community engagement liaison
(Cel) Position for two years to
support energy and environmental
-
>> okay. So the amendments here
on page 4 line 1 though 4 and
complete the file and release
the funds for the finance
committee and on page 4 lines
through 12 no new position will
be funded unless approved by the
future ordinance thank you,
supervisor chan by ordinance in
the continued position authority
prior to the reserve hearing and
completed file is there a motion
to accept the amendment seconded
by supervisor fielder.
>> without objection those
amendments are approved
(Gavel)
And now take this.
>> same house, same call.
(Gavel)
Whoops without objection the
resolution is as amendment amend
now the
(Gavel)
MADAM Clerk next item, please.
>>
in a program, entitled "
state
vocational rehabilitation
services program,"
for the
period of JULY 1, 2025, through
JUNE30, 2028.
>> okay. >> um, when I talked
about all the work this clerk
was doing working with the
amendments which couldn't happen
without the clerk on page 2 um,
line 5 through 9 and 22 to 23
adding references for the finish
line impacts and striking all
references to the adoption on
page 3 line is there 5
alexander's the requirements for
the authority to review we file
those funds to the land use
committee and on page 3 adding
clarification none shall be
approved without authorization
and should be identified with
the authority prior to the
reserve hearing and considered
with the completed file is there
a motion to accept the
amendments as property by
supervisor walton and seconded
by supervisor chan without
objection those amendments are
approved
(Gavel)
Now on the resolution as amended
take that.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection this is
approved.
>>
calendar year 2025, from the
united states department of
transportation, federal highway
administration for the
development and deployment of-
>> okay. And here we have
amendments on page 3 adding
reference to the finish line
requirements.
>> and will be determined this
has impact on page 4 upgrading
the verbiage and on page 4
adding reference to the finish
line impact for the review of
file and release to the finance
committee and on page 5 adding
clarification no new position
funded by this grant unless
approved by a future-prior to
the release of reserve and
considered with the completed
file is there a motion to accept
the amendment as proposed.
>> moved by supervisor chan.
Do I have a second?
>> supervisor fielder so we can
take that motion without
objection those amendments are
approved
(Gavel)
And take that.
>> same house, same call. This
resolution as amended is
approved.
>>
>> MADAM Clerk next item,
program entitled "
calaim ji path
round 2 funding-san
francisco,"
for the period of
MAY 26, 2023, through OCTOBER
31, 2024. >> thank you, MADAM
Clerk.
>> um, here the amendments are
on page 2 line is there 1 and 2
and 6 and 7 striking the
demonstration on page 2
clarifying the file will be
reviewed for completeness and
adding clarification no new you
position will be added without
ordinance and two positions will
be identified and the authority
prior to the release of this
completed file. And can we have
-can someone move the
amendments seconded by
supervisor dorsey. Um, let's see
-we can take those amendments
without objection they were
approved
(Gavel)
And on the resolution as amended
take that.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection the amendment
is adopted
(Gavel)
MADAM Clerk next item, please.
>> MR. PRESIDENT I'm going to
read-item 10 so we can put
this in line with the others as
you're taking those
pedestrian safety improvement
project for grant performance
period from grant contract
execution through AUGUST 30,
2029;-
>> great. Supervisor chan has
moved to send this to the budget
and finance committee and
supervisor fielder has seconded
that. And I think we can take
that motion.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection. The motion
motion passes.
>>
>> all right. And item
department of transportation to
fund the bayview connections:
phase 1 harney way bus rapid
transit (Brt) And cycletrack
project,-
>> so here the amendments on
page 4 line 16 and 17 striking
reference to the finish line
impact la determined this didn't
have-and on page 19 reaching
the determination and accepted
moved forward by supervisor chan
and seconded by supervisor
fielder without objection those
amendments are approved and
amend take that.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection this
resolution as amended is adopted
services (Rss) Funding-san
francisco,"
for the period of
OCTOBER 1, 2023,through
SEPTEMBER 30, 2026.
>> okay. And here I believe one
amendment on page 2 line 6 and 7
and 11 and 18 places the fund
for the authority to review
those funds to the budget and
finance committee. There a
motion to accept the proposal by
supervisor walton and seconded
by supervisor dorsey and take
that motion without objection
these amendments are approved
(Gavel)
And think is resolutions amended
take those.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection this
resolution is adopted
(Gavel)
And MADAM Clerk next item,
please.
>>
peaks promenade project, for a
grant performance period from
SEPTEMBER 20, 2024, through
MARCH 15, 2027; approve the
grant-
>> all right. Here the
amendments are on page 2 line 20
and 23 for the impact for the la
has determined has a finish line
impact and think page 3 through
9 due to the lack of the finish
line support place those on the
board of supervisors reserve and
with the complete file and refer
to the budget and finance
committee and motion to accept
the amendments proposed by
supervisor walton and seconded
by supervisor sherrill without
objection approved and now
amended take that.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection the resolution
as amended is adopted
(Gavel)
MADAM Clerk
grant amount of $13,635,302 from
the centers for disease control
and prevention for participation
in a program, entitled-okay.
The amendment here on page 1
line 8 and 9 adding a charter
section 9.188 language and page
12 making and adding the charter
section language on page 2 line
15 through line 3 page 3
delegating the authority to
release the fund to the-
clarifying the award be approved
a motion to accept the maximums
as proposed?
>> motion made by supervisor
chan and seconded by supervisor
sherrill and take that motion
without objection those
amendments are approved
(Gavel)
On the resolution take that.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection the resolution
as amended is adopted
as amended is adopted MADAM
Clerk next item, please.
>> 15. Resolution retroactively
authorizing the department of
public health to accept and
expend grant increase in the
amount of $13,431 from the
national institutes of health
through the university of texas
southwestern medical center, for
a new total amount of $104,508
for-okay. An amendment on
page 2 line 14 24r50 page 3 for
the fund for the board of
supervisors and delegating
authority and motion to accept
the amendment by supervisor chan
and seconded by supervisor
fielder and we can take that
these amendments without
objection those amendments are
approved and on resolution as
approved take that.
>> same house, same call. As
amended
amended is adopted MADAM Clerk
next item,
program entitled, "
comprehensive
opioid, stimulant, and substance
use site-based program,"
for the
period of OCTOBER 1, 2024,
through SEPTEMBER 30, 2027. >>.
Okay. Number of amendments on
page-adding the only package-
page 2 line 2 through 5 adding
the charter section language and
placing funds on the board of
supervisors reserve and review
the file for the budget and
finance committee and on page 2
line this and adding the
language is there a motion to
accept the amendments moved by
supervisor mahmood and without
objection those are approved and
take that.
>> same house, same call.
Without objection this
resolution as
resolution as adopted MADAM
Clerk next item, please.
>>
agency (Epa), to fund the san
francisco waterfront
emissions-free ferry system for
the period of JANUARY 1, 2025,
through DECEMBER 31, 2028.
Striking that language and on
page 4 adding the finish line
impact and determined and page
4.
>> line 12 due to the lack of
finish line place those on the
board of supervisors reserve and
sending this to the budget and
finance committee is there a
motion?
>> moved by supervisor chan and
seconded by supervisor fielder
without objection those
amendments are approved and take
that.
>> same house, same call..
Without objection the resolution
is amended is adopted
(Gavel).
>> MADAM Clerk please next
item, please.
>> MR. PRESIDENT that
concludes that portion of our
agenda.
>> well done.
>> okay.
>>
(Clapping.)
Yeah, thanks everybody. Good
work and I think there are next
stop on the agenda is the
imperative.
>> the in in memoriams will be
in memory of beloved individual
on behalf of the
on behalf of the supervisor
melgar for the latest pete and
in that brings advertised the
end of our agenda any more
business.
>> that concludes our business
for today.
>> MADAM Clerk if no further